<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A raging wave foming out his own shame. Or, An answer to a book lately published by Richard Hains (a person withdrawn from) entituled, A protestation against usurpation. Wherein appears such a measure of envies bitterness heaped up, pressed down, and running over, as the like in some ages hath not appeared, by his many false accusations, and malicious insinuations, thereby to provoke (if possible) both the chief magistrate, and all men of what degree soever, to have suspicious thoughts of the innocent, easily proved to have no other fouudation [sic] but his own evil imaginations. : Wherein also the church of Southwater by him contemptuously rendered papistical in their act of withdrawment from him, is vindicated and cleared, first, by apostolical authority, secondly, by Rich. Haynes his own pen. / Written by Matthew Caffyn ...</title>
            <author>Caffyn, Matthew, 1628-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C207A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173317</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097591</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097591</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171202</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171202)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2567:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A raging wave foming out his own shame. Or, An answer to a book lately published by Richard Hains (a person withdrawn from) entituled, A protestation against usurpation. Wherein appears such a measure of envies bitterness heaped up, pressed down, and running over, as the like in some ages hath not appeared, by his many false accusations, and malicious insinuations, thereby to provoke (if possible) both the chief magistrate, and all men of what degree soever, to have suspicious thoughts of the innocent, easily proved to have no other fouudation [sic] but his own evil imaginations. : Wherein also the church of Southwater by him contemptuously rendered papistical in their act of withdrawment from him, is vindicated and cleared, first, by apostolical authority, secondly, by Rich. Haynes his own pen. / Written by Matthew Caffyn ...</title>
                  <author>Caffyn, Matthew, 1628-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith at the Elephant and Castle, near the Royal Exchange, in Cornhill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Haines, Richard, 1633-1685. --  New lords, new laws, or, A discovery of a grand usurpation.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Discipline.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171202:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RAGING WAVE Foming out his own Shame.</p>
            <p>OR, An ANSWER to a Book Lately Publiſhed by <hi>Richard Hains</hi> (a Perſon withdrawn from) Entituled, <hi>A Proteſtation againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein appears ſuch a meaſure of Envies bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs heaped up, preſſed down, and running over, as the like in ſome Ages hath not appeared by his many falſe accuſations, and malicious inſinuations, thereby to provoke (if poſſible) both the chief Magiſtrate, and all men of what degree ſoever, to have ſuſpicious thoughts of the innocent, eaſily proved to have no other foundation but his own evil Imaginations.</p>
            <p>Wherein alſo the Church of <hi>Southwater</hi> by him contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſly rendred Papiſtical in their act of withdrawment from him, is vindicated and cleared, Firſt, by Apoſtolical Authority, Secondly, by <hi>Rich. Haynes</hi> his own pen.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Matthew Caffyn</hi> of <hi>Horſham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own cauſe ſeemeth just, but his Neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him, <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 8.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Neither can they prove the things whereof they accuſe me, <bibl>
                     <hi>Act. 24.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle, near the Royal Exchange, in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171202:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171202:2"/>
            <head>A Raging Wave foming out his own ſhame.</head>
            <p>SUch is the nature of this my neceſſary oppoſition againſt the proteſtation of my cauſe-leſs adverſary, as that it may ſeem uſeful for Chriſtians to remember how the ſaints and ſervants of God formerly did not only meet with perills without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, but alſo perils within <hi>among falſe bretheren.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. and particularly how <hi>Alexander the coper-ſmith</hi> (he very likely that <hi>Paul</hi> had excommunicated that he might learn not to blaſphme. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20.) <hi>did Paul much evil, and greatly withſtood his words.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14.15. as alſo how the Apoſtle propheſied that <hi>in the latter dayes</hi> (by reaſon of ſome profeſſors, <hi>having the form of godlineſs,</hi> becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as nevertheleſs were <hi>incontinent, lovers of themſelves, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, blaſphemers, falſe accuſers, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, heady, high-minded, from whom the Apoſtle adviſeth Timothy to withdraw) perillous times ſhould be.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Now to what degree theſe Scriptures are fulfilled in this my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries heaping up ſo many ſlaunders, and abuſive ſuggeſtions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the innocent; with an out-cry made of uſurpation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of authority againſt them that both <hi>feareth God, and honoureth the king,</hi> (and ſo all, through grace, eaſily proved to be no other then his own evil imagination) the reader is deſired to make judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by his following treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>Richard Haynes</hi> in his firſt page declares his hopes that the Congregation <hi>will not take occaſion from his tenderneſſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his duty in the acknowledgment of his ſin against God, thereby to juſtifie cruelty againſt him:</hi> we the congregation of <hi>Southwater</hi> being aſſembled, and in the conſideration of this matter, do hereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare our readyneſſe to comply with his hopes concerning us therein, being well aſſured, that although it appear moſt true (as himſelf here, and elſewhere ſuggeſteth) that before the controverſy about his patent, <hi>R. H.</hi> had been conquered by ſin committed againſt the moſt high, yet may we not, nor are we conſcious to our ſelves that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171202:3"/>at any time we did, act or maintain any action of cruelty towards him upon that or any other account; but as <hi>R. H.</hi> hath publiſhed his hopes concerning us in the caſe aforeſaid: we likewiſe are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling here to publiſh our hopes, or deſires concerning him, namely, that he would (in the fear of him, into whoſe hands to fall is a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing) be aware of that ſpirit of exceſſive bitterneſſe, and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſſe againſt <hi>M. Caffyn</hi> the perſon reproving him (in private) for that his ſin committed againſt the moſt high, and that laboured for ſome time conſiderable to reſtore him: whoſe bitterneſſe thus continuing and abounding againſt him, gives us juſt occaſion (at leaſt-wiſe) to queſtion that unfaignedneſſe of his repentance for the ſame, which here willingly he would poſſeſſe the reader with the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of, <hi>pa.</hi> 6. and very probably may to a greater degree be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by him that knows more (it ſeems) then we do, who neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for good cauſes (as was then at leaſt-wiſe conceived) did not publiſh the ſame at the time of <hi>R. H. his</hi> withdrawment, in order to the tryal and examination thereof; there being in his underſtanding (as alſo in ours) ground ſufficient for other cauſes to withdraw from him: and the rather do we here publiſh theſe our hopes or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of him, for that he may be well aſſured, while here he thus lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth up voice, with ſo much pretended diſcontent againſt both us, and <hi>M. C.</hi> for our excommunicating him about the Patent, 'twill be evidenced that himſelf elſewhere hath readily confeſſed that his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt <hi>M. C.</hi> was not ſo much upon that account, as for the caſe in difference before.</p>
            <p>Now as touching our withdrawment from <hi>R. H.</hi> as one unworthy of communion, the reader is to obſerve, that we (upon his earneſt requeſt) did give him in writing a paper contayning the grounds of our proceedings: the which ſurely had he intended honeſtly and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, he would have acquainted the reader with it, and ſo endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſhew (if he could) the unſoundneſſe and imperfection thereof: but oh what may be juſtly ſuſpected, when he ſhall not only be ſilent therein, but ſhall alſo in the mean time frame to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and publiſh to the world an abuſive account, with ſuch altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, additions, and omiſſions, as might beſt ſuit with his envious diſpoſition, and then fight againſt the image thus of his own fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſetting up, as an odious and deteſtable thing? <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he, pa. 5.) <hi>this new Lord</hi> (contemptuuſly ſpeaking of me) <hi>by his own arbitrary, new laws, without one word of God for it, pronounced
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171202:3"/>me excommunicate, meerly for this thing, purely civil, alledging that whether lawful or unlawful it was all one: firſt, becauſe that it was of an evil report amongſt the common ſort of the world, ſecondly, that it was an offence to the weak brethren.</hi> Now that this account of <hi>R. H.</hi> is falſe and abuſive in five reſpects may appear.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by his ſaying, that he was excommunicated <hi>meerly,</hi> and in page the 4th. ſaith, <hi>only,</hi> for this thing purely civil, meaning the patent; whenas he may well know, and as the congregation (in their paper ſent unto him) declares, that for his unworthy carrage in cenſuring his brethren after an unchriſtian manner, together with his reſolutions to ſtand in the defence of his Patent, notwithſtanding all that was objected to the contrary, they proceeded againſt him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in that while the congregation with my ſelf, judged and alſo recorded his practiſe to be ſuch as was an occaſion of ſcandal and reproach to the truth, he (the better to render us odious, and himſelf innocent as one may think) ſaith, that judgment was made againſt his practiſe, becauſe it was of an ill report amongſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of the world, (as if, among men ſober, ſerious, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, we had no cauſe to judge it of an evil report) the which, as it was never in our hearts to think, ſo was it never declared by us, nor is there one word of that nature in the account which the Church gave him in writing of their proceedings.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in that while the congregation with my ſelf in the ſaid account ſignified their being troubled and offended with this his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious proceedings, ſo much ſavouring of his preferring the gain of this world before the honour of the goſpel, thus lyable to reproach, while he a profeſſor thereof was both publickly in the market, and elſewhere reproachfully ſpoken of, to the great ſhame of ſome that heard it, and the trouble and offence of all, when they underſtood it; while (I ſay) we thus ſignified our trouble and offence, he abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively declares his withdrawment to be upon the account that his patent deſign was an offence to the weak brethren, whom (he ſaith) he enquired after that he might know who they were, as if there had been another party more ſtrong that were not offended with him, who yet, to gratifie the weak brethren, conſented to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication; and the more intollerable is this abuſe, when it ſhall be conſidered with the account we firſt gave him, wherein weak brethren is not ſo much as once named, or ſignified; together with our proteſtation ſince againſt it, as a conceit of his own framing, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171202:4"/>which alſo (as himſelf confeſſeth in this very page) is denyed by us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in that while he knows that the congregation with my ſelf did excommunicate him, as himſelf confeſſeth, <hi>pa.</hi> 4. he renders it here as if I ſingly (after a Lordly manner) did it.</p>
            <p>Fifthſy, in that while endevours were uſed by me and others (and more might have been, had he not obſtinatly refuſed to reaſon the caſe with me) to convince him from Gods word of the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his proceeding, and as himſelf confeſſeth, that Gods word was produced, <hi>pa.</hi> 22. yet ſlanderouſly doth he here declare, that without regard to the lawfulnes or unlawfulneſs thereof, he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared excommunicate, without one word of God for it: whoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe herein may further appear in our anſwers to his exceptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our proceedings: only obſerve, that while here he ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſaith, that there was no regard to Gods word in the judgment given againſt him, he elſewhere in <hi>pa.</hi> 29. (ſpeaking of what the congregation had regard unto) in like manner ſlaunderouſly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that they did it <hi>only</hi> (Mark) to pleaſe their Idol, forgetting ſurely what he had ſaid in the 25. <hi>page,</hi> namely, that the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did it <hi>only</hi> (Mark) to pleaſe the curſing and reviling ſons of <hi>Belial:</hi> to which <hi>two only's</hi> of his, I may well here add a third, <hi>only,</hi> and ſay, that theſe malitious and inconſiſtant ſuggeſtions of his ſerves <hi>only</hi> to repreſent him a man making little conſcience of what he ſaith, and ſo his words deſerving little credit.</p>
            <p>The firſt exception which <hi>R. H.</hi> makes againſt our proceedings, is with reſpect to the matter, we having (ſaith he <hi>p.</hi> 4.) no juſt cauſe or warrant for the ſame.</p>
            <p>In anſwer, we firſt ſay, that if it were deemed by him (or ſhould be ſo thought by any other) that in our zeal and care to preſerve the truth (which we believe and profeſs) blameleſs, and that none ſhould have occaſion of ſtumbling, or to ſpeak evill of the good ways of God, if (I ſay) upon this account we ſhould be thought by him inregularly to have proceeded (which yet we believe not) ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were there not the ſpirit of malice and bitterneſſe (for ſome other foregoing cauſe) ruling in him, he would not thus revile and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully ſpeak of us, nor uſe thoſe ſwelling words of uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tyranny, Popiſh infallibility, accompanied with abuſive com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons, as if herein we might be numbred with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe extravigant thoughts, and pernitious expreſſions (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſeems to out-ſtrip the deeds of many men meerly moral:) we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171202:4"/>wiſh God may never lay it to his charge hereafter.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, whereas Gods word declareth, that <hi>to condemn, or falſly accuſe the juſt, is abomination to the Lord.</hi> Pro. 17.15. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. we judge our proceedings againſt <hi>R. H.</hi> is warrantable, for that he (as one too much governed by that ſpirit that is the <hi>accuſer of the brethren</hi>) thus did in his fury cenſure and condemn ſome of his brethren (in the midſt of the congregation) and this without either offering proof to juſtifie the ſame or his humility to juſtifie him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: and whereas 'tis written 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32.33. that Chriſtians (in order to their ſeeking the profit of others that they might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, more then their own profit, as alſo in order to their doing all things to the glory of God) ſhould <hi>give none offence, neither to the Jew nor the gentile, nor the Church of God,</hi> but rather be thinking of, and preſſing after, <hi>whatſoever things are of good report, Phil.</hi> 4.8. it being (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15.) contrary to charity, yea and expreſly <hi>evil, to eat fleſh, or drink wine, or any thing</hi> (Mark) <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the brethren ſtumble or are offended or made weak, Rom.</hi> 14.20.21. (that is, when the forbearance of eating, or whatever elſe is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive or ſcandalous, is no tranſgreſſion of Gods law) whereas (I ſay) 'tis thus recorded, we judge our proceedings againſt <hi>R. H.</hi> juſt and warrantable, for that he thus coveting and graſping after the wedge of gold, did not only thereby greive and offend Chriſtians here, and elſewhere that heard thereof, but alſo, and more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thereby deliver up the cauſe of the goſpel as lyable to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and crucified by the tongues of men, while he a profeſſor thereof, thus to their great offence proceeded: although his ſo much affected gain thereby (as ſome think) hath been put into ſuch a bag of holes, as that there will ſcarce remain thirty pence to be thrown up in the day of his recantation, if God in mercy ſhall offer him ſuch a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>But whereas it poſſibly may be pleaded, that the caſe of <hi>R. H.</hi> is not any thing that is ſinful in it ſelf, and ſo no juſt cauſe for profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors to be greived or offended, nor others to ſtumble thereat, or ſpeak evil thereof. My anſwer is, that he may well know that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors generally never ſo eſteemed his caſe, but rather that his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent-deſign ſavoured much of covetouſneſſe, for that ſome parſons cleanſing the ſame ſeed of non-ſuch to his knowledge, before his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veting the Patent, and after another manner too, and without any information from him, whereby as good ſeed as his (if not better)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171202:5"/>was procured; and whom <hi>R. H.</hi> confeſſed (before witneſſes ready to atteſt it if need be) that by the law of God and man they might do it: that ſome ſuch perſons (I ſay) are notwithſtanding by this his Patent not only lyable to be hindred of this their lawful privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but alſo declared by him to have no right thereunto. But if otherwiſe <hi>R. H.</hi> his Patent ſhall be deemed lawful in it ſelf (as by ſeveral it is) yet is it no more then what might be pleaded concerning thoſe meats, which the Apoſtle pronounced clean, and lawfull to be eaten both by the law of God and men, who never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs ſtrictly charged the Chriſtians of thoſe times (as they ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred charity on the one hand, and their avoiding evill on the other hand) not to eat the ſame when any thereby was greived or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: and ſurely much more reaſon have Chriſtians (in all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) to yeild their necks to this Apoſtolical yoke, when not only the offences of their brethren within, but alſo manifeſt danger of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling thoſe that are without, ſhall be inviting and obliging them thereunto; nor may this be reſtrained to ſuch meats only, becauſe the Apoſtles words doth not only imply, but plainly expreſs <hi>any thing elſe</hi> beſides that, might, as well as meats, occaſion ſtumbling or offence, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. to which agrees the Apoſtles advice elſewhere; ſaying, <hi>whether ye eat, or drink, or whatſoever (mark) ye do, do all to the glory of God,</hi> which that they might effectually do, in the next words, he adviſeth them, <hi>to give none offence to any,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.32.</p>
            <p>But oh that <hi>R. Haines</hi> would conſider from his own pen (if not from the Apoſtles) the juſtneſſe and legalitie of our proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him! leſt otherwiſe he give further cauſe and ground to men thereby to believe that 'tis a ſpirit of envie, for ſome other cauſe, and not conſcience of his duty towards God, as he would inſinuate, that provokes him to this kinde of undertaking: however thus he declareth (<hi>pag.</hi> 22.) that if the ſence of the Apoſtles words had been, <hi>That Chriſtians ſhould give no offence to the curſing and reviling ſons of Belial, or to the Church of Antichriſt, as for laws and prerogatives what have we to do with them? that then</hi> (Mark) <hi>our practiſe had been ſomewhat authentick:</hi> that is to ſay, undeniable, and approved of all men.</p>
            <p>Now that the unbelieving Jews and gentiles, whom Chriſtians on the one hand were obliged to give no offence unto, as on the other hand not to offend the Church of God, were very many of them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171202:5"/>ſuch, that is, men greatly polluted with ſin, is againſt all contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction true, for that not only the publicans and ſinners of the Jews, but alſo the profeſſing ſcribes and phraiſees were found defaming and reviling both Chriſt and Chriſtianity; nor ſurely can <hi>R.H.</hi> (as clouded as he is) think otherwiſe of the prophane and Idolatrous Gentiles; and ſo were they truly the Church of Antichriſt, that is (as ſurely he intends) ſuch as were againſt Chriſt; and ſo doubtleſs no more deſerving (nor yet ſo much) Chriſtians carefulneſs not to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them, then the many perſons that profeſs Chriſt in our times: nor may he think himſelf innocent nor free from tranſgreſſion, if he ſhould (or any others with him) conceive the Apoſtles charge, to intend only, that Chriſtians ſhould give no offence to thoſe Jews and Gentiles that were more ſober, ſerious, and honeſt, then thoſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and ſinners amongſt them were, ſince even ſuch men in this caſe as well as others (if we may not ſay more then others, they being ſo much concerned therein) were in like manner offended with him, and condemned his practiſe; or will he think it becomes him to publiſh thoſe that have ſhewed their diſlike to his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be ſuch only as are the curſing &amp; reviling ſons of <hi>Belial?</hi> if ſo, and that ſuch his publication were upon juſt grounds, yet ſhould he not (if he had learned of Chriſt, who ſo much tendred the good of publicans and ſinners) be regard-leſs of, or by any means deſpiſe, their low eſtate; but alas! it ſeems he has rather of late learned of that perveſe and froward generation of the Phariſees, and ſo is found walking in their ſteps, upbraiding Chriſtians now (as they did Chriſt then) for being <hi>ſuch friends to publicans and ſinners</hi> (the revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and defaming ſons of men) while they only now (as their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt did then) tender the good of their ſouls, and therefore at all times unwilling that any occaſion of ſtumbling, ſhould be given them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if</hi> R. H. <hi>ſhall ſtill object and ſay, that although the Apoſtles charge in relation to the not giving offence to ſinful men ſhould be as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and ſo your practiſe thus far juſtified, yet it may not be thought that the principles of the Apoſtles could admit them to ſay alſo, as for laws and prerogatives what have we to do with them? upon which alſo I concluded the authentickneſs of your practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My anſwer is, that ſo far their principles did admit (as their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe declares) as to endeavour that Chriſtians ſhould forbare their right to, and privilidge of eating, thoſe meats, which by the civil
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171202:6"/>laws, and prerogative of the chief magiſtrate, they might partake of: and ſo practically they declared that they had nothing to do with the laws and prerogatives of their rulers, as from thence to plead the lawfulnes of eating thoſe meats, when the eating thereof apparently tended to the greiving and ſtumbling others (though they deemed it their weaknes to be greived at it) and ſo that great and mortal duty of charity thereby neglected towards them: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Apoſtles had many bitter and cruel adverſaries, yet was there none (at leaſt wiſe as we read of) ſo vile and baſe as thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to publiſh them as ſuch that contemned the laws and prerogative of the civil Magiſtrates; and yet alas <hi>R. H.</hi> ceaſeth not thus unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to deal with me for no other cauſe ſave only that I (with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) endeavoured to ſtop him in his Patent-deſigne, and not to have pleaded the priviledge of the law, and his Majeſties prerogative, when his deſign ſo apparently tended to the grieving the brethren, and ſtumbling others (though he had deemed it their weaknes to be grieved at it) and ſo that great and moral duty of charity thereby neglected towards them.</p>
            <p>But oh how great is the obſcurity of the (much to be lamented) fruit of this mans enmity! that he doth not conſider (while he ſo much ſpeaks of contempt of authority) that there is no law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding or requiring men that they muſt have (or elſe rebels by law) but rather that perſons (whoſe ingenuity juſtly requires it) may have Patents (marked as a priviledge grantable by his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties prerogative (whoſe prerogative therein what Chriſtian ever queſtioned) therefore (as himſelf pleads) <hi>there being no law requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it, there can be no ſuch tranſgreſſion</hi> (as the contempt of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) in the perſwading from it, thoſe pious ends aforeſaid being the ground of ſuch their endevours, ſo that ſtill the reader may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that our proceedings againſt <hi>R. H.</hi> is not only juſtified by Gods word, but by his own pen alſo.</p>
            <p>If yet this be not ſufficient, the reader may here alſo read his own words, which elſewhere we have under his hand, as thus, <hi>if (ſaith he) my brother being a Jew, newly converted to the faith, and whilſt he is young and weak, dares not eat ſwines fleſh, and therefore will have no communion with thoſe that he knows to eat thereof, becauſe the law forbids it, ſhall I therefore eat ſwines fleſh whereby to offend this weak brother? God forbid</hi> (ſaith <hi>R. Haines) I with the Apoſtle will ſay, that I will eat no meat while the world ſtands, rather then he for whom Chriſt died
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171202:6"/>ſhould periſh, for who ever (ſaith he) doth otherwiſe, becomes an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> (and as elſewhere he ſaith) if obſtinate, <hi>deſerves publickly to be blamed,</hi> and if not then publickly to be excommunicated, if ſtill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, let him aſſigne a reaſon whereof ſuch an offender ſhould be publikly blamed: now as from hence our publick rendring him as an offender, ſeems to be declared authentick; ſo alſo that his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples (and that ſince this controverſie too) about the not offending or not greiving one the other, are of far greater ſeverity &amp; much more ſtrictneſſe, then can poſſibly appear in our practiſe againſt him; ſo far as to publike blame. Firſt, becauſe his principle is, that whoever doth not in charity avoid the offending and greiving <hi>one only weak brother</hi> (and when he is grieved too, for that which is neither the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the law of God nor man, as muſt be allowed concerning ſwins fleſh, yet ſuch a one ſaith he) <hi>is an offender:</hi> where our practiſe in blaming him was for his want of charity manifeſted by his offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and greiving many, to wit, the congregation, as alſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brethren related to other congregations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe his principle is, that whoever doth not in charity avoid the offending <hi>one only weak brother;</hi> without any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt occaſion thereby offered for others, either to ſpeak evill of the ways of the Goſpel, or injuriouſly to ſtumble thereat, for that they very generally believe the lawfulneſs of eating ſwines-fleſh, <hi>is not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding an offender;</hi> when as our practiſe in blaming him was, his want of charity manifeſted by his offending and grieving many, to wit, the congregation, as alſo many others, with manifeſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereby offered for others both to ſpeak evill of the wayes of the Goſpel, and injuriouſly to ſtumble thereat, for that they very generally did not believe the lawfulneſs of his Patent-proceedings.</p>
            <p>And whereas his only plea to evade ſelf-condemnation, and our juſtification is (as he hath declared) <hi>that in all caſes as it hath relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to matters of religion and worſhip, the ſtrong ought to bear the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the weak, but in things meerly civil, and never by any law forbidden, as there can be no reall ground for any ſuch offence, ſo doth there not lye any ſuch obligation,</hi> whereas (I ſay) this is his only plea, the reader is,</p>
            <p>Firſt, to obſerve that while he (not the Scriptures) makes this curious diſtinction, the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om.</hi> 14.21. <hi>that 'tis not good to eat fleſh, or drink wine, or any thing</hi> (mark) <hi>whereby thy brother ſtumbleth, or is offended.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:171202:7"/>
            <p>Secondly, as he ſaith there can be no reall ground for any offence from ſuch caſes as are meerly civil, and never by any law forbidden, ſo likewiſe muſt he conclude that in the caſes of ſwines-fleſh, and things offered to Idolls, there is no reall ground for offence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they lawfully may be eaten; but then,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as he concludes the weak brother (that dares not eat ſwines-fleſh) to be conſcionably offended, becauſe it was once for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden; in like manner might he conclude (however we do) that perſons may as conſcionably be greived at, and offended with, the civil undertakings of men, wherein the ill ſavour of covetouſneſs doth appear, for that covetouſnes was alwayes forbidden; and ſurely a converſation unſpotted from the world, hath as much rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to pure religion, as ever the not eating of ſwines-fleſh had: but perhaps he will pleade that perſons apprehenſions of covetouſneſs in ſuch caſes may proceed from ſome miſtake through weakneſs; and what then, if certainly ſo it be? the like muſt <hi>R. H.</hi> confeſs concerning his weak brother, whoſe apprehenſion of ſin in the eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſwines-fleſh, proceeded from miſtake through weakneſs; and yet would he not offend him (if we may believe him) by no means.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, as by the eating meats offered to Idols, ſome were made liable thereby to offend, and ſo the eating thereof became ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; ſo in like manner by the undertakings of men in civil caſes, as ſometimes they are circumſtances (and as <hi>R.H.</hi> his caſe was) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be made liable thereby to offend, that is, by ſpeaking reproachfully of, and hardening themſelves againſt, the good wayes of God and ſo likewiſe ſuch civil undertakings (as are only lawfull, and ſo not ſinful in the neglect thereof) may become ſinful.</p>
            <p>The premiſes then conſidered, amounting to no leſs then plain e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence from the word of truth, juſtifying our practiſe, which (it ſeems was ſo firmly received by, and grounded in <hi>R. H.</hi> heretofore; as that even yet while breathing out his envy againſt me, his own pen is made uſe of to juſtifie our practiſe to be ſomewhat authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, yea and his own principles (ſo far as to publick blame) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be ſuch as out-ſtrips our practiſe in relation to ſuch as greive their brethren, together with his reaſon-leſs, religion-leſs, preſident-leſs, as alſo civil law-leſs ſuggeſtions againſt me, as if I were one diſobedient to authority barely for diſſwading from that which was never commanded by authority: theſe things together
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171202:7"/>conſidered, may it not rationally be conceived, that this (not to be paralled) publication wherein ſuch an out-cry of uſurpation, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, contempt of authority is made, proceeds from ſome other foundation than our excommunicating him for the cauſes aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Whereupon as to his ſeeming willingneſs that the reader ſhould make obſervation of the good diſpoſition and frame of his ſpirit <hi>in his performance of family-dutys, and the government of his family, ſo as that (he ſaith pa.</hi> 18.) <hi>in many yeers he hath not known any thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by them worthy of publike blame;</hi> my anſwer is, that had it not been for the many tranſgreſſions, (ſometime before this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie about his Patent, ſince which he never had communion with us at the table of the Lord) committed ſomewhere in the family, and not voluntarily confeſſed, as ſince he moſt falſly hath ſuggeſted, but through care and diligence diſcovered, with occaſion given of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued diſſatisfaction; I am much perſwaded that theſe extravagant thoughts and pernicious actions of his envy againſt me had never appeared: but I comfortably remember <hi>that ſnares were laid here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore for Gods people that reproved in the gate, Iſa.</hi> 29.21.</p>
            <p>But to return, having ſhewed, that his exceptions againſt the matter of our proceedings, is groundleſſe, and that his proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt us elſewhere, as not proving him a tranſgreſſor of Gods law, before the fentence of excommunication, is truth-leſs, that which remains in the next place worthy the readers conſideration, is his exceptions againſt the manner of our proceedings, wherein he declareth there was <hi>diverſe irregularities,</hi> but there mentions none, only I find in his proteſtations (<hi>pa.</hi> 6.) two things whereat he ſeems to remain diſſatisfied.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>that he was not ſuffered to know who his accuſers were, either as they were weak brethren, or as they were no brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> What can <hi>R. H.</hi> be ignorant who were his accuſers, while he ſo well knows, and ſo often confeſſeth, that the congregation did excommunicate him for crimes (in their account) thus publick? or would he have the reader believe that the congregation did excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate him for thoſe things which they never accuſed him of? as for his ſaying, that he knows not his accuſer, <hi>as they were weak bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> (thereby ſuggeſting another party more ſtrong, not offended with him, and ſo not accuſing him upon the aforeſaid account:) my anſwer is, that there was no ſuch diſtinguiſhed party for him to know, as the Churches account of their proceeding (greatly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171202:8"/>by him, and accordingly ſent unto him) ſufficiently ſheweth: as touching others (not under the notion of brethren) that did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him, whoſe names (he ſaith) <hi>he was not ſuffered to know,</hi> if thereby he intends to inſinuate into the Readers underſtanding, that we either knew of none, or very few that ſpoke diſdainfully of his proceedings, I do not ſuppoſe that he can poſſibly in theſe parts (at leaſt wiſe) proſelite many, if any one, into that belief; nor hath he (whatever his intent may be) any occaſion to our remembrance thus to ſpeak, ſave only the perſon having given an inſtance in the meeting how <hi>R.H.</hi> his name was blaſted in the market, upon the aforeſaid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, with ſuch reflections upon the congregation, as was greatly to the ſhame of ſome that heard it, did forbear to mention the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons name ſo ſpeaking, to prevent ſome evill that ſuppoſedly might follow the publication of his name.</p>
            <p>His ſecond <hi>Objection</hi> is, <hi>that he was not ſuffered to treat with the Congregation, in order to the ſatisfying the offended, by reaſon of my continuall interruptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply,</hi> when <hi>R.H.</hi> appeared at our Church-meeting (after ſome words in order to the right ſtating of the caſe) he was deſired to ſpeak what he could in vindication of his practiſe, if ſtill he deemed it lawful, it being upon our parts fairly to treat with him therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, he, contrary to our expectations, and contrary to what himſelf for many years had allowed, when offenders have been treated with, yea and (as I am much perſwaded) contrary to the allowed and reaſonable practiſe of all Churches under what name ſoever, he (I ſay) did not only require my ſilence in the debate of the matter, but alſo did, notwithſtanding the Congregations de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared diſlike to his uſurping requirement, continue his reſolution to ſtop my mouth, not allowing me the priviledge of other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: yet nevertheleſs it being upon our hearts at that time to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour his conviction, did permit him to reaſon with ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but when at any time I perceived occaſion and opportunity to offer, and accordingly did ſomething to the matter in hand as well as others, being alſo deſired by the congregation ſo to do, he (while groundleſly ſuggeſting uſurpation and Lordlineſs in others) did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally after a Lordly manner uſurp a power (the proper right of no member, much leſs of one called to the aſſembly as an offender) and withſtood me, preſſing ſtill for my ſilence; whereby the liberty of reaſoning intended him, he partly deprived himſelf of: ſo that in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171202:8"/>ſubſtance my endeavours, (with the reſt of the members) and this too by conſent of the Congregation at that time, is deemed by him, and now publiſhed as ſinful interruptions on my part; <hi>the truth of this above-ſaid account, we the Congregation do hereby teſtifie,</hi> and may it not be thought fit, that for any Church to ſacrifice up that power and thoſe priviledges that God hath given them, and their elders for their preſervation, to the envious wills and ſelfiſh ends of offenders, would be not only a reaſon-leſs ſcripture-leſs, but alſo a very injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (if it may not be ſaid alſo ridiculous) practiſe, and preſident; for that thereby a wide door would be opened to all deceivers and Apoſtats, when at any time they ſhall (and ſurely were ſuch a thing granted, at all times they would be ready and bold to) make at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts in Congregations of what profeſſion ſoever; there to divide and to devour, if when ſo they do, it may be declared lawful for them to command the elders and miniſters ſilence, (and if them, conſequently any other that they ſhall think are able to diſcover the error of their principles) and that the ſeveral Congregations are bound in duty to gratifie ſuch deceivers or Apoſtates, by their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>R. H.</hi> ſhould (for I know not that he doth) intend inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of another kinde, through too much earneſtneſs, or quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſpirit (though occaſioned through his haughtineſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs) yet to what degree ſoever any thing of that nature ſhall be evidenced, he may be aſſured that none of us ſhall be aſhamed to confeſs the ſame,</p>
            <p>As touching his exceptions in the third place, wherein he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth our proceedings to be <hi>both ſinful as to our ſelves, and injurious to him,</hi> we anſwer, that the intent of Chriſt in giving forth, and the deſigne of Chriſtians in their proſecuting the ordinance of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, was, that tranſgreſſors might again be reſtored, when the Churches counſel and advice did not effect it; therefore if <hi>R.H.</hi> be injured by it, 'tis through his abuſe of Chriſt his ordinance, and his condition is the more to be lamented: as to its being <hi>ſinful to our ſelves,</hi> we know no ſuch thing, but rather the performance of our duty towards God and him: as for <hi>letting in all kinde of uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, and ſubverting the Churches priviledges</hi> (ſuggeſted alſo by him we conceive it only his vain immaginations, for how it ſhould ſo do, he declares not: as <hi>for our practiſe being ſean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous to the better and the more ſober and judicious ſort</hi> (as he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171202:9"/>alſo inſinuateth) the contrary to us is moſt evident; and we doubt not but that many from their own experience will be able (with us) to teſtifie his miſtake herein; though they may (by their ſo doing) be excluded, by this ſpirit of envie, from the number of ſober and judicious perſons, and counted amongſt the baſer ſort of men: yet is it not to us a matter incredible, that ſuch (if there be any to be found) that have ſo large a faith to believe all that he ſuggeſteth againſt us to be true, that ſuch perſons (we ſay) ſhould render ſuch manner of proceedings with offenders to be ſcandalous, for our ſelves do thereby declare them to be ſo; as touching his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious ſuggeſtion, that <hi>our practiſe tends to the infringing the lawfull power of the ſupreme Magiſtrate,</hi> eaſily appears both illegall and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational, upon the aforeſaid account, that there being no poſitive law requiring <hi>R.H.</hi> that he muſt have his patent, there could be no ſuch tranſgreſſion in us perſwading him from it; and more eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may our innocency herein, and his inſolency appear, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration that ſo great a number of other perſons bearing their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony (not only as well, but much more then we) againſt his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent) are notwithſtanding by <hi>R. H.</hi> juſtified from any ſuch contempt of authority; our meaning is, thoſe many perſons from ſeveral Towns and Pariſhes, as well perſons of quality as others, that by their hands ſubſcribed to a paper did appear againſt him, as alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with the aſſiſtance of Council learned in the law, as Sir <hi>Ed. Thurlow</hi> of <hi>Rigate,</hi> Sir <hi>Hen. Peckham</hi> of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> before the Lord Keeper of the Broad ſeal, where, after ſome debate of the caſe, he having alſo able Council on his ſide, his expectation was then fruſtrated, and his deſign rejected as unreaſonable, and illegall; for ſaid the Council, <hi>what if a man ſhall deviſe a new way to threſh his corn, ſhall he therefore have a Patent, ſurely no:</hi> and what then may theſe be deemed innocent, (as doubtleſs he conceives them ſo to be) in their oppoſition, for the ſake of mens outward advantages, and this too after his Majeſties grant of the ſame? and may we be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to the world, as contemners of his Majeſties prerogative in our oppoſition, for the ſake of mens foul-advantages, without evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent demonſtration of his malice againſt us?</p>
            <p>In the Apoſtles times matters of wrong were puniſhable (as now they are) by the civill laws of the Kings and rulers then in being, yet ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. <hi>dare any of you having a matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, go to law,</hi> &amp;c. what, would <hi>R. H.</hi> if he had lived in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171202:9"/>thoſe times have publiſhed the Apoſtles as one that contemned the Kings prerogative? if not, then what beſides a bitter root of envy (for ſome other cauſe) is the ground of this reaſon-leſs, and alſo law-leſs publication?</p>
            <p>Beſides, if what is reported to us be true, that the ſtatute, upon which Patents are grantable, is to gratifie the ingenuity of ſuch as by conſiderable charge, or long ſtudy ſhall invent ſomething for publike good (as we incline to believe, becauſe the <hi>Lord Bridgman</hi> with Councill learned in the law put a ſtop to his deſigne, and alſo becauſe <hi>R. H.</hi> would as yet never produce the ſtatute in ſuch caſes provided) if this, we ſay, be true, then it remains yet a Queſtion to ſome whether this Patent was not fraudulently procured; that is to ſay, by ſuggeſting ſomething of ingenuity, ſtudy, or charge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what in uprightneſs he could do: for ſince the common cuſtome of men long before was to dry the ſeed of Clover, and then to threſh it (for which no man meerly mortall coveted a Patent) we know not how reaſonably to think that to dry the ſeed of <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuch,</hi> and then to threſh it (which <hi>R. H.</hi> counts a worthy invention) eſpecially conſidering ſuch a preſident before, ſhould be numbred among the deſerving arts and inventions of ingenious men.</p>
            <p>As to the inhuman and unchriſtian ſuggeſtions of <hi>R. H.</hi> againſt me, in relation to contempt of authority, ſo often repeated by him (wherein he hath out-done the deeds of the worſt of men to me, for what end other then (perſecutor-like) to provoke (if poſſible) the chief Magiſtrate againſt me, I know not; I only ſhall adde this more, that ſuch has been my doctrine whereever I came, with reſpect to Chriſtian obligations, <hi>to be ſubject to the higher Power, and to obey every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> ſuch alſo has been my publick reaſonings, and private conferences in divers places, in oppoſition to that ſpirit that <hi>deſpiſeth dominion,</hi> ſuch has been my forwardneſs, not only that <hi>Feſtus</hi> his civill laws ſhould be obſerved, but that his perſon alſo ſhould be honoured, as <hi>Moſt noble Feſtus,</hi> though as to matters of religion he be found telling <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>he is beſides himſelf,</hi> yea, and ſuch has been in that caſe my principles many years ago publiſhed in print (which is yet viſible) ſubſcribed by me, and many others, as that I do not ſuppoſe the unworthy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations of a man thus over-maſtered with the ſpirit of envy, will gain credit among many, if any,</p>
            <p>But I may not omit here to let the Reader underſtand how <hi>R. H.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:171202:10"/>having endeavoured (as aforeſaid) to render me an object of hate to the chief Majeſtrate, deſcends (<hi>pa.</hi> 28.) to provoke (as may be thought) the Judges of Aſſize and Seſſions againſt me, ſaying; that I have complained againſt them as acting rigidly and illegally: but in what, when, or where he aſſigns not, nor ſurely will he ſay, that for ſeveral years we have had any communion about ſuch perſons, nor that he did give me the leaſt <hi>Item</hi> of ſuch a thing before, this publication being my firſt information; which ſurely may be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient demonſtration of the unworthineſſe of his ſpirit: but while I know nothing of this nature, which he abuſively ſuggeſteth againſt me, this I well know, that my principles have been (as my practiſe have declared when I have been called before perſons of ſuch quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) not only <hi>to ſubmit to the King as ſupream, but alſo unto governours</hi> (as Judges) <hi>ſent by him;</hi> and if it any time there ſhould be required, that, which ſhould be thought by any to ſavour of rigidneſs, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſeem to them unlawfull, or illegall, and ſo in conſcience to God they cannot actually obey, that there remains no other law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full way for ſuch to take, ſave only patiently to ſuffer, or humbly to intreat favour: nor is this all, for in <hi>pa.</hi> 18. he deſcends to perſons of an inferior quality, ſaying, that I rebuked him for being conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with great perſons, to raiſe in them alſo (as may be thought) a prejudiciall opinion againſt me: and from thence he deſcends in the ſame page, ſaying, that I alſo forbid him to be a peace-maker amongſt his neighbours; (he being extreamly unwilling, as may hereby be thought, that any from the higheſt to the loweſt, ſhould have a good opinion of me) to all which I anſwer, that there is no more true, then that from ſome fears, and godly jealoſie, that he might, among ſome perſons of quality, take that liberty, which would neither be honourable to the truth, nor conduceable to their good; as alſo from ſome fears, that while his underſtanding was deeply exerciſed about civil controverſies, he might (as ſome have) forget his Chriſtian obligations, and ſo misbehave himſelf, no more (I ſay) true, then that upon this account I did cautionally ſpeak ſomething to him about it; the truth of which, our approbation then, as well as now, of perſons that occaſionally are converſant with perſons of note, and alſo that are concerned in matters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, ſufficiently demonſtrate: nor yet is this all, for (in <hi>pag.</hi> 18.) he alſo declareth, that for what he can underſtand familie-du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties is ſpoken againſt, rather then encouraged, thereby to beget (as one
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171202:10"/>at leaſt wiſe may think) an ill opinion among the ſeveral ſorts of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of our times concerning me, whenas there is (to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) no other foundation for theſe unworthy reflections (as my doctrine and practice to many may declare) ſave only that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I have dropped ſome words, importing ſome diſlike to ſuch proceedings of men therein, as ſeem to be meerly cuſtomary, and more eſpecially, when they thereby pretending religious diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhall in the mean time live in religious actions, &amp; paradventure in their families too, (as <hi>R.H.</hi> may well know ſome have done) &amp; for that end has been my ſo ſpeaking that Chriſtians ſhould (both in their families and in their cloſets) not only be frequent, but more fervent, more ſenſible and ſerious in the performance of their duties therein: as touching the diſcouraging his ſervants (whereof alſo he ſpeaketh) none ſurely can reaſonably think that we (who have conſcionably refuſed to communicate with him) can in conſcience encourage any to joyn in communion with him, who hath thus heaped up ſin up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſin to ſo great a degree.</p>
            <p>Again, what beſides <hi>R. H.</hi> his continued wrath againſt me (which faith the Apoſtle <hi>worketh not the righteouſneſs of God</hi>) could move him elſewhere (<hi>pag.</hi> 6.) to declare, <hi>that I condemned Patents in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> whereas he hath lying by him theſe words of mine under my hand, namely, <hi>that for perſons to have Patents in ſeveral caſes as they may be circumſtanced, is both legal and reaſonable,</hi> let the Reader judge.</p>
            <p>In the next place, the reader may underſtand, that as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for which, and the manner in which he was proceeded againſt, he hath abuſed us; ſo alſo, that he (no leſs extravagantly) proceeds to abuſe us, but more eſpecially my ſelf, (<hi>pag.</hi> 3.) as a perſon that will not come to the light, leſt my deeds ſhould be reproved, as if I were conſcious to my ſelf of irregularity in our proceedings, and ſo have withſtood his appeal to others.</p>
            <p>Concerning which, all may underſtand, that he had (according to the cuſtome of our Churches) free liberty to make his appeal to any of the many Churches in the Counties adjacent (though com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſome neighbour-Church has been the perſons appealed unto) but (to uſe his own words elſewhere) <hi>he utterly refuſed ſo to do,</hi> and why? becauſe faith he (further to uſe his own words) <hi>moſt of them were inferiour, and that I was adored</hi> (as he is pleaſed to term it) <hi>and eſteemed by many of them:</hi> ſo that it ſeems ſuch as have eſteem for me, are not judged by <hi>R. H.</hi> ſuitable perſons to hear and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171202:11"/>this controverſie, and yet doth he (and oh that he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how envy hath confounded him!) talk much of impartial juſtice.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, all may know, that if <hi>R. H.</hi> had, notwithſtanding his appeal to ſome one of thoſe many Churches aforeſaid, remained diſſatisfied, or if otherwiſe no determination ſhould have been made; he then might have freely made his appeal to our quarterly meetings (conſiſting of diverſe elders and brethren from ſeveral congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) nor is this all the liberty which he might freely have had, but upon his remaining disſatisfaction, might alſo have freely made this appeal to the general Aſſembly at <hi>London:</hi> nor yet is this all, but when at the firſt general Meeting his appeal (for ſome cauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to be mentioned) could not be then received, I then did free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offer (the truth whereof <hi>R. H.</hi> ſurely will not oppoſe) that if the preſent Aſſembly would chooſe out ſix men or more, I ſhould be willing that they with the Quarterly meeting in the Countrey ſhould be the only Judges of the matter depending betwixt us, and that I and the Congregation would not be concerned, ſave only to give evidence, but he (as before) utterly refuſed it: nor yet is this all the liberty or ways of condeſcention that was allowed <hi>R.H.</hi> for when at the next general meeting he appeared with urgency not common, for a hearing of the matter (they being ſuch as himſelf made choice of and had eſteem for) 'twas declared to him (after ſome debate) that they would condeſcend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o his motion, though ſo to do croſſed the method of proceedings that formerly they had (upon good grounds) agreed upon, and which for the ſake of ſome others was not granted: and ſo the matter was examined, judged, and determined, to the utmoſt of their preſent capacity, and their reſult recorded, as himſelf confeſſeth, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. the which when <hi>R.H.</hi> had peruſed, he in the face of the Aſſembly told them, that he contemned what they had done: the which is confeſſed by him, <hi>p,</hi> 10. but in better words he preſents it to the Reader, ſaying, <hi>that he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified his diſlike of their reſult, with his reaſons for it:</hi> now in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of ſuch our conſtant freedom, that he ſhould make his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal (not to this or that Church of our chooſing) but to what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church himſelf ſhould make choice of, among the many Churches in ſeveral Counties, being by him utterly refuſed; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the conſideration of ſuch his inſolent contempt of the reſult drawn up by the general aſſembly, conſiſting (as he may well
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171202:11"/>know) of the Meſſengers, Elders, and brethren (the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Churches both in the City and Countrey; one would think, that, were there an abſolute death of Chriſtianity in him, and but humanity only remaining, he would not have thus abuſively publiſhed me, or any others, as perſons refuſing to have the caſe heard or tried, as frequently he ſuggeſteth.</p>
            <p>And whereas he is pleaſed to ſay <hi>pag.</hi> 11. <hi>that he doth not perfectly underſtand the reſult of the General Aſſembly, though as far as he did underſtand it, the effect of it was, that we ſhould reverſe the ſentence of excommunication;</hi> the reader may obſerve, how extreamly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing he is, that it ſhould be underſtood, that the general aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie did at all favour us, to prevent which, he plungeth himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to confuſion, and ſelf-contradiction, (and ſo 'tis happened unto him according to what is written, <hi>where envying is, there is confuſion and every evil work</hi>) for in the <hi>page,</hi> juſt before, he tells the Reader that he ſignified his diſlike of their reſult, and his reaſons for it; whereby 'tis evident, that he not only underſtood it, but alſo well knew, that the effect thereof was not, that we ſhould reverſe it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he would have the Reader underſtand, that he ſhewed his diſlike to the Aſſemblies reſult, becauſe they had juſtified him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned us.</p>
            <p>As touching that conference we had firſt about it in a Coffee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, while repreſented by him, a meeting of ſome great authority, in truth 'twas only intended (as ſignified to me by letter) a private conference about the matter with a few perſons, not any particular Church, nor any particular perſons choſen by the Churches, nor the Church of <hi>South-water</hi> who excommunicated <hi>R. H.</hi> ſo much as ſent unto, to be preſent there; whereupon as in truth they could not, ſo in truth they did not pretend to any power to determine the matter, but plainly and publickely declared the contrary, nor was <hi>R. H.</hi> himſelf willing to refer the matter to them (while he blames me upon that account unleſs his declared reſolutions to ſtand by, what end thereof others ſhould make according to the unerring rule in his judgment, may properly be called the referring it.</p>
            <p>Yet is it true, that this conference intended with a few only, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing known, in the city, ſeveral others unconcerned, came, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to rule and expectation <hi>R. H.</hi> engageth one to be there, that did not belong to any of the baptized congregations in communion with us (whom I ſuppoſe) he conceived ſufficiently averſe to me,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171202:12"/>who concerned himſelf (with ſome others) in favour to his caſe, more then any of thoſe that did belong to us, and that ſent and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified their deſires to me of ſuch a conference; and whereas he would poſſeſs the Reader that I have given a falſe account of what was ſpoken by ſome at this conference, my anſwer is, that as I am not conſcious to my ſelf of any ſuch thing, ſo alſo, that they, whom it concerns, never as yet ſignified any ſuch thing to me, nor do I ſuppoſe that they ever will thus judge of me, as <hi>R. H.</hi> doth, when their word at that time ſpoken ſhall be brought again to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance: and although it be true that ſome preſent at this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference do entertain in communion one that hath a Patent, yet is it not true that the ſame perſon hath a Patent upon like conſiderations as <hi>R. H.</hi> hath his (as he would have the Reader believe) for that the ſaid perſons Patent was not (as ever I heard) attended with any reproach or ſcandal to his profeſſion, to the probable injury of mens ſouls ſtumbling thereat, nor yet with the grief and offence of his brethren deeming it inſufferable, (all which were the moſt evident attendances of <hi>R. H.</hi> his Patent) and beſides while <hi>R. H.</hi> his inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as he terms it) of threſhing <hi>non ſuch</hi> after the ſame manner, as for many years men uſed to threſh <hi>Clover,</hi> hath been (by men learned in the law) judged undeſerving, this mans art, and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the other hand hath been judged ſo far deſerving, and to advantage tending, as that his Majeſties pleaſure is to entertain him as his Hydrographer (if I miſtake not the title).</p>
            <p>And whereas he further ſuggeſteth to the Reader <hi>that I very diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly withſtood his appeal afterwards to the general Aſſemblie at</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>notwithſtanding my promiſe to do what I could to have it there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and this to his conſiderable coſt by reaſon of his witneſſes that he brought thither, which (ſaith he) had I been honeſt and a Chriſtian, might have been prevented, by my telling him before, that there it could not be heard, pa.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>My anſwer is, that in all honeſty to him as a Chriſtian, I did tell him (<hi>Jam. Smith</hi> a living witneſs thereof being with me in <hi>R. H.</hi> his parlor) that by reaſon of an agreement formerly made by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly, the caſe depending between he and us, could not be there heard <hi>(unlikely therefore, that I ſhould tell him I would do what I could that it might be there heard and determined)</hi> till ſuch time he did firſt make his appeal to the Countrey Aſſemblies, and then it might: for which cauſe I in reaſon could not ingage the Church, or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171202:12"/>their meſſengers to repair thither for a hearing, having alſo perfect knowledge that ſeveral caſes preſented to the general meeting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and of great concernment too, had been for the preſent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood upon the ſame account, even, their not having made their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal elſewhere before: now had he not been already corrected for this abuſive charge, that is my not telling him before (for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of his expence that his caſe could not then be heard, I might reaſonably have attributed it to his forgetfulneſs, but when the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall conſider (as juſtly he may) that he had now lying by him the teſtimony of my ſelf and <hi>Jam. Smith</hi> under our hands, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt exception ſince againſt it, both that he was, and the very place where he was told of it: what can this his publication now be leſs then a manifeſtation of his willingneſs to abuſe me? and more eſpecially when it ſhall be conſidered with his own confeſſion (<hi>pa.</hi> 6.) that they (to wit the general aſſembly) <hi>would not</hi> (to uſe his own words) <hi>hear the matter except it were examined by ſome other Congregation before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas he would have the Reader believe, that I was the only inſtrument to hinder the hearing of his caſe at this meeting, the truth is, that neither I nor any other, but himſelf only, was the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to hinder it, for that he refuſed to make his appeal firſt elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, according to the method of our proceedings, which upon good cauſes formerly we had agreed upon; and whereas the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation at <hi>Southwater</hi> determined not to appear at the general Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie at <hi>London,</hi> becauſe they underſtood that by reaſon of their former agreement, the caſe depending between them and <hi>R. H.</hi> would not then be tryed; if afterwards <hi>I</hi> had ſaid (though his bare ſaying that <hi>I</hi> did, who hath ſaid ſo much extravagantly is little) that if the generall Aſſembly, through his exceſſive urgencie, ſhould incline to the hearing his caſe, when by their own former agreement the congregation of <hi>Southwater</hi> was abſent, <hi>I</hi> could (and very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably too) put it off for that time, till another opportunity when the congregation might be there, yet doth not this, in the leaſt, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch a withſtanding his appeal, as he would have the Reader underſtand; for that it was conſtantly allowed him there to appeal after his appeal, firſt in the Countrey, is not only declared by us, but alſo confeſſed by himſelf; <hi>pa.</hi> 6. but what may juſtly and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be concluded from <hi>R.H.</hi> his ſo great earneſtneſs to have his caſe heard at the general Aſſembly, and when they did undertake
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171202:13"/>it, he not only found diſregarding, but alſo contemning, what they had done; beſides that the impartiall juſtice, which he pretends to be zealous for, to be done by others, is no other then himſelf to be quitted, and others condemned, according to his own judgment, let the Reader judge.</p>
            <p>As touching his frequent ſuggeſtions <hi>that he hath been put to great expences by his having up ſeveral witneſſes,</hi> let him reflect upon his own folly therein, for had he received the information given by me (and alſo by others) that his caſe could not be heard there, till he firſt appealed in the Countrey, he might thereby have pretended both his trouble and charges: nor may he only herein reflect upon his own folly, but alſo in his having up witneſſes the laſt meeting, when his caſe was examined, for while he (to the abuſe both of me and the Aſſembly) gives ſuch an account (<hi>pa.</hi> 10.) as ſuppoſethto the Reader, that the examination of his witneſſes was refuſed, in truth they were never called forth by him to teſtifie any thing for him (as <hi>I</hi> know of;) but while here he relates ſo much of his expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive troubles, in reference to his witneſſes, <hi>I</hi> doubt he conſidereth not (as iuſtly he might) his expences otherwiſe, and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly his expences to his tranſcriber (he being a man learned in the law) who, either that he might the better revenge himſelf upon the object of his envy, or that he might ſeem to men eminent, or both, who (<hi>I</hi> ſay) to uſe his own words elſewhere, <hi>ſupplied with amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments his matter, where he had not made it true engliſh, or perfect ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>R.H.</hi> doth further declare, that though <hi>it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſuall for ſuch caſes to come to the general meeting, yet his caſe might, becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I gave him liberty to appeal to whom he would in City or Country.</hi> My anſwer is, that <hi>I</hi> gave him no other liberty to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal (as <hi>I</hi> know of) but to the City and Country as aforeſaid, that is, to any whom he would of the Country-Aſſemblies, and then to the general aſſembly in the City: and ſuch liberty himſelf ſurely will not deny but that 'twas always granted him: nor indeed could <hi>I</hi> give him any other liberty, by reaſon of another agreement made by the general Aſſembly, whereby the Churches in the City were unconcerned; yet if <hi>I</hi> had, and the Congregation of <hi>Southwater</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, without which no reaſonable plea can be from it to engage them to anſwer to ſuch his appeal, as yet we are blameleſs; becauſe he as yet never did make his appeal to any particular Church in the City or Countrey: ſo that ſtill it appears, 'twas his obſtinacy againſt the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171202:13"/>regular way of appealing, and not our withſtanding his appeal, that in any meaſure hindred him.</p>
            <p>To conclude then, as from the whole, ſince nothing arbitrary without regard to Gods law, nor any thing of contempt to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties law, nor any thing ſavouring of Popiſh infallibility, or u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation, but rather ways of condeſcention, appears in our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings firſt and laſt, againſt <hi>R. H.</hi> (the foundation pieces on which he builds his conceit, that we properly may be called <hi>Papiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Baptiſts;</hi> whether this monſtrous birth, (or new name of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt) may not be rationally concluded to proceed forth from the womb of envy, in the beginning begotten by him, who is the grand accuſer of the brethren, let the Reader judge.</p>
            <p>Now at laſt <hi>R.H.</hi> having obſtinatly refuſed our conſtant readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to anſwer to his appeal, if made to any of the Country Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, our condeſcending offers to be judged by a ſelect number of the general Aſſembly with others in the Countrey, and laſt of all having ſignified his diſlike to the reſult and determination of the general aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly made, touching the caſe depending between us, he now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to a new offer, (not now to appeal, but) to refer the matter in controverſy, but to ſuch perſons, and upon ſuch terms, as that he well knows (as at leaſt-wiſe may be thought) we cannot reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſubmit unto, and thereby creates an occaſion to make agreat out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry in the world againſt us, as ſuch that will not come to the light, leaſt our deeds ſhould be reproved: oh the ſubtilty, but alas the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of the device!</p>
            <p>The perſons nominated by him to whom this matter ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, are <hi>the Elders and Miniſters of the baptized Congregations in and about</hi> London, whereby in all likelihood he intended, the Reader ſhould underſtand, that they were ſuch perſons as were in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with us only, whenas the Elders and miniſters the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the baptized Churches in <hi>London</hi> that are in communion with us, were part of the general Aſſembly that have already deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the matter to his diſlike: as for the Elders and miniſters of ſome other baptized Congregations in <hi>London,</hi> that by reaſon of ſome difference in principles, are not in communion with us, and ſo have not uſually concerned themſelves with us, nor we with them, ſome of whoſe names are hinted at by <hi>R. H.</hi> in his 12. page, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Mr <hi>G.</hi> Mr <hi>J.</hi> with ſeveral others, well known to ſome of us that are of the ſame different perſwaſions: as for ſuch (we ſay) we look
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171202:14"/>not upon our ſelves in reaſon obliged to refer the matter unto them, conſidered with the Congregation they belong to, or others that may be allowed as aſſiſtants with them, much leſs to particular perſons pickt out of them by an envious ſpirit, ſuch as (he paradventure thinks) are moſt averſe to, and diſaffected with us; and in the mean time barely to allow us the liberty to chooſe one Country-meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: but here alſo by the way the Reader may further make obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his ſpirit towards me; for ſpeaking of others that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vys not, he calls them meſſengers, but ſpeaking of me whom he doth envy in the very line before, he ſaith Apoſtle, <hi>pa</hi> 15. (thereby to raiſe in the Reader thoughts of admiration and diſaffection) though he cannot; but know that I never pretended my ſelf to be, nor was thought by any others to be, but in the ſame capacity with thoſe called by him Meſſengers, in divers reſpects beneath, and much inferiour to thoſe ſent out heretofore as the Apoſtles of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But then as to the terms upon which this reference is propoſed to be, to which he would have us foreengage, they are ſuch alſo as ſurely becomes not a man that pretends to ſuch ingenuity, as to teach the whole Nation how they ſhould become rich, for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>R. H.</hi> having choſen all the referees himſelf (one only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon out of the Countrey left to our chooſing) he now propoſeth that thoſe that are <hi>parties may not be allowed as witneſſes,</hi> which is to ſay in all plainneſs, that all thoſe that are capable of being witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, ſhall be no witneſſes, for the Congregation (with my ſelf) are parties; and who then ſhall be their witneſſes? if as to that one clauſe in our charge against him in relation to that ill report, and ſcandal occaſioned by his coveting his Patent, he thereby intend that we ſhould engage ſuch perſons not under our diſcipline, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at <hi>London</hi> to give evidence, I would then know by what rule, and by what means ſuch a courſe may be taken? although when done, they, knowing nothing of what otherwayes he ſtands char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with, nor any thing in relation to the manner of our proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt him, can poſſibly give no evidence as to thoſe caſes: and therefore I ſay ſtill who then ſhall be our witneſſes?</p>
            <p>Secondly <hi>R. H.</hi> allows ſuch to be witneſſes <hi>as are indifferent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> that is to ſay, truly inrerpreted, we ſhall have no witneſſes; for that no ſuch indifferent perſons, not related to us, were amongſt us (at the time of our proceedings againſt him) to take cogniſance
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171202:14"/>for what, and after what manner he was proceeded againſt, but the congregation only.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, while thus he would at once ſtop all our mouths (who only are capable of witneſſing any thing againſt him, he provides a way to open wide the mouths of ſuch as ſhall witneſs for him, for whatever they ſhall ſay, his propoſal is (<hi>pa.</hi> 15.) that we fore-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage they ſhall be <hi>heard and credited,</hi> Mark, <hi>credited:</hi> without the leaſt proviſion made for any juſt acception, becauſe he ſaith <hi>they were never proved to be falſe witneſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What? is this the man that tells the Reader of his great zeal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter impartial juſtice, who, having not only ſlited the reſult of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly (conſiſting of the Meſſengers, Elders, and brethren from all parts, but alſo ſlited and rejected all the Churches as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) in the ſeveral Countys adjacent, becauſe (to uſe his own <hi>I was eſteemed by many of them,</hi> and having now ſound out (being much at <hi>London</hi>) ſome that (he probably thinks) hath little or no eſteem for me, and that belong not to our Churches, and have not communion with us, that (with ſome others) he would refer the matter unto, now to propoſe ſuch unequal and unreaſonable terms too; I ſay again, is this the man that tells the Reader of his zeal for impartial juſtice? and not only ſo, but, as that which renders his condition the more to be lamented, alſo is found (<hi>pa.</hi> 12.) not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid <hi>to make ſolemn proteſtation in heaven, before God the ſearcher of hearts, that his deſigne is only</hi> (Mark) <hi>to obtain impartial juſtice:</hi> what credit may be juſtly given to ſuch a mans words, let the reader judge.</p>
            <p>Beſides, ſuch are, and ſo great a number, his trangreſſions hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up ſince his excommunication, namely, falſe accuſations, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling and reproachful expreſſions, as alſo his malitious ſuggeſtions, as if we were Papiſtical Baptiſts, for no other caſe but our conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable teſtimony againſt his coveting the Patent (whereby thoſe of differing perſwaſions from us that have ſignified their diſlike to his proceedings therein, are ſuggeſted by him likewiſe to be Papiſtical as well as me) together with what was chargeable before the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, but for ſome cauſes then omitted, which favour intended him therein (though upon a deſigne to do him good) perhaps might be (however, ſo 'tis thought by ſome) diſpleaſing to God, he being altogether unworthy thereof, as his deportment ſince ſeems to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare; I ſay, ſuch and ſo great is the unworthineſſe that he ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171202:15"/>in (juſtly requiring his recantation to be as publike as his ſlanderous proteſtation, as that it juſtly leaves, not only our ſelves, but others alſo, under diſcouragements to trouble our ſelves with him while in ſuch a ſpirit; being ready to think that the ſame migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand of God that hath already begun to rebuke this ſpirit of envy that was in his abetter, is the only ſufficient and likely means to effect his real reformation, and ſo his reconciliation: and ſo much the more diſcouraged are ſome, while they conſider, that, if we had no juſt cauſe (as indeed we have) to accept againſt the referring the controverſy, <hi>&amp;c. R. H.</hi> himſelf (notwithſtanding all his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes) is not willing to refer the matter indeed (as ſome well know that have treated with him thereabout) his profers having been no more (what he may do provided he might have the liberty to refer the matter to whom, and after what manner he pleaſeth I know not) then that <hi>he would with contentment ſtand by what end others ſhould make of it, according to the unerring rule</hi> (Mark) theſe are his own words, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. which (as himſelf to one or more have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained it, and as the words ſeem to import) is juſt nothing at all; for if the judgment given ſhall not be according to the unerring rule in his judgment, he preſently proceeds to judge his Judges, and ſo all the trouble and pains ends with no effect, except thereby further to demonſtrate his folly.</p>
            <p>And whereas I have ſaid, that God hath already begun to rebuke the ſpirit of envy, my meaning is, that whereas a certain perſon formerly abetting, and aſſiſting <hi>R. H.</hi> in his envious deſigne againſt me, was in humility made to confeſs the ſame, and declare as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe may certifie, whom it may concern that I being under the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hand of God, am made freely, and heartily to declare, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I have formerly been a co-actor with</hi> Rich. Haynes <hi>in the publication of ſome things, wherein</hi> Mat. Caffyn <hi>is accuſed as an enemie to the Kings laws, and his Prerogative, together with other things relating to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, and the like, that (I ſay) therein I have done very evilly, and do judge that it was diſorderly, and envyouſly done by me, and ſo am heartily ſorry for it, and alſo farther declare, that, having diſcourſe with</hi> M. C. <hi>am ſatisfied towards him; and do deſire from my heart to be reconciled to the Congregation; declaring alſo, that I do greatly fear that by my abetting, and ſtanding by</hi> R. H. <hi>as I have done, that thereby I have done him wrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:171202:15"/>
            <p>Since which time, the ſaid perſon is reconciled to the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and whereas this ſo ſudden, and great alteration by the hand of God tended ſo much to the ſtripping and laying open the nature of that envious ſpirit, by which <hi>R. H.</hi> (and his conſederate) was governed; he preſently ſuggeſted abroad, that the ſaid perſon, notwithſtanding his confeſſion of envy ruling in him, ſtill remained ready to declare, <hi>that what he had informed him of, was all true;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by inſinuating that which is moſt falſe, as the perſons own teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may evidence, which is thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas</hi> Rich. Haynes <hi>ſince is pleaſed to report, that though I acknowledge the irregularity and enviouſneſſe of my proceedings, yet that I do ſtill declare, that what I informed him of, was all true, as if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I had ſtill matters of charge againſt my brethren: theſe are thereupon further to teſtifie, that what things ſoever of truth formerly declared by me to</hi> R. Haynes, <hi>which then in the ſpirit of malice uncharitably and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſively was wreſted, I now in the ſpirit of charity do judge, that there was no juſt cauſe thereby given me to accuſe my brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>R. H.</hi> once again ſuggeſteth to the Reader, that ſomething he forbears to mention, that is reported concerning me: and wherefore? <hi>in kindneſs (ſaith he) and in love to regain me:</hi> now whether he that obſerves his writings may believe, that he in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of love to me thus inſinuateth (which whoever ſhall, hath ſurely attayned to a larger degree of faith then many others) or whether it be a deſigne of envy for want of ſomething evident where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to accuſe me, ſuggeſteth hereby a mountain, which if he ſhould have plainly declared (his own conſcience told him perhaps) would not have appeared a mole-hill: whether (I ſay) the Reader may believe it a deſigne of love to regain me, or a deſigne of envy to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe me is the queſtion to be reſolved; and ſurely not difficult to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, when it ſhall be conſidered, 1ſt, that he neither before this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, nor at any time ſince, informed me of any ſuch report, and how then ſhould it be a deſign of love to regain me? while I know not in the leaſt, what it is that is reported, nor 2ly would he give me any preſent account of this report (what he may in future do I know not) though provoked by letter (ſent by me, by the hands of his neighbour <hi>James Smith</hi>) to inform me with this provocation, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>leſt otherwiſe his refuſing ſo to do</hi> (that is, to diſcover the report, and the reporters) <hi>ſhould be judged, and conſtrued his not knowing any thing mrterirll by others repoeted as evill in me, and ſo a moſt abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171202:16"/>ſuggeſtion:</hi> and how then this his pretended deſigne of love to regain me, (while he thus keeps me ignorant of the evill that he pretends by his words to gain me out of) can reaſonably be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then a deſigne of envy to abuſe me, let the reader judge.</p>
            <p>And whereas 'tis written that <hi>the wicked are like the troubled Sea, that cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſteth up mire and dirt:</hi> whether <hi>R. H.</hi> his condition doeth not much correſpond thereunto, caſting up ſuch foul and dirty inſinuations, the like not to be ſound (ſurely) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong any ſort of men that know us, let the Reader judge by this further ſaying of <hi>R.H.</hi> namely, <hi>that he cannot imagine what ſhall hinder you</hi> (meaning the congregation) <hi>from impriſoning, baniſhing, and burning of people for not ſubmitting to your government, if power and opportunity were not wanting:</hi> what ſhall we render evill for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill? God forbid.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>R.H.</hi> is pleaſed to compare the proceedings of us the congregation, to the illegall proceedings of one (ſuppoſedly) in authority that ſhould become a uſurper and Tyrant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſaith (<hi>p.</hi> 28.) <hi>that our conſciences muſt needs teſtify the truth thereof,</hi> &amp;c. we the congregation thereupon do hereby teſtifie (before all men) <hi>the falſhood thereof, and proteſt againſt the ſame as a ſcandalous, and pernitious parable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, omitting ſeveral other injurious inſinuations, <hi>as if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons dared not without my conſent by lawfull means to provide for their families,</hi> and ſuch like reaſonleſs clamors, not likely to have enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynment in the hearts of reaſonable men: I now conclude, wiſhing from my heart, that God may not lay theſe, many ſlaunderous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, and envious inſinuations to his charge, ſo as hereafter to reward him accordingly: for as God deſired not, neither may we, the death of a ſinner, but rather that he return and live; for the which, that it may ſeaſonably be accompliſhed in him to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Goſpells honour, nay prayers have been, is, and ſhall be to the almighty for him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
